<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The ivglers discovered, in two letters writ by Lievt. Col. John Lilburne, prerogative prisoner in the Tower of London, the 28. September, 1647. to his Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax, Captaine Generall of all the forces in England and Wales, discovering the turn-coat, Machiavell practises, and under-hand dealings of Lievt. Gen. Cromwell, and his soone in law, Commissary Generall Ireton, and the rest of their hocus pocus faction in his Excellencies Counsell of Warre, the first of which letters thus followeth. Unto which is annexed some advice to the private soldiers.</title>
            <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88203</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2123</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E409_22</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7139</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873087</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873087</idno>
            <idno type="VID">161200</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88203)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161200)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 65:E409[22])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The ivglers discovered, in two letters writ by Lievt. Col. John Lilburne, prerogative prisoner in the Tower of London, the 28. September, 1647. to his Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax, Captaine Generall of all the forces in England and Wales, discovering the turn-coat, Machiavell practises, and under-hand dealings of Lievt. Gen. Cromwell, and his soone in law, Commissary Generall Ireton, and the rest of their hocus pocus faction in his Excellencies Counsell of Warre, the first of which letters thus followeth. Unto which is annexed some advice to the private soldiers.</title>
                  <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
                  <author>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, Baron, 1612-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>11 [i.e. 12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>P. 11, 12 misnumbered 12, 11.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "8ber [i.e. October] 1st. 1647.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireton, Henry, 1611-1651.</term>
               <term>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658.</term>
               <term>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657 --  Imprisonment --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Detention of persons --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:161200:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <div type="title">
               <p>THE IVGLERS DISCOVERED, In two Letters writ by Lievt. Col. <hi>John Lilburne,</hi> prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative priſoner in the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> the 28. <hi>September,</hi> 1647. to his Excellency Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> Captaine Generall of all the forces in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> diſcovering the turn coat, Machiavell practiſers and under-hand dealings of Liew. Gen. <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and his ſoone in law, Commiſſary Generall <hi>Ireton,</hi> and the reſt of their <hi>Hocus Pocus</hi> faction in his Excellencies Counſell of Warre, the firſt of which Letters thus followeth. Unto which is annexed ſome advice to the private Soldiers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <opener>
                  <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have yeſterday ſeen a paper comming from yourſelfe, and your <hi>Councell of Warre,</hi> wherein there is mention made of my ſelfe, &amp; and though it doe not reach what I ſtand in need of, yet can I not but judge my ſelfe very much obleiged unto your honour, and the rather becauſe the firſt motion made unto you by my true friends the Adjutators, found ſuch a noble and reſpective acceptation at your hands, (as my intilligence gives me to underſtand it did) though it received obſtructions from others, <note n="*" place="margin">Viz. <hi>Commiſſary Generall Ireton. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> from whom I might have challenged more intereſt then from your ſelfe. <hi>I</hi> beſeech your Excellency give me leave to ſtate my caſe unto you, which is thus, upon the 10. <hi>Iune</hi> 1646. I was by warrant from the Houſe of Peers, brought to their barre, to anſwer ſuch things, as I ſtood charged with before their Lordſhips, concerning a Pamphlet intituled, <hi>The juſt mans juſtification,</hi> or a letter by way of plea in bar, and hereof he ſhall not faile, as he will anſwer the contrary at his perrill. <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Which ſaid Order you may verbatum read in the</hi> 3. <hi>pag. of my book called the free mans freedom vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated: in which you may alſo read what paſſed betwixt us at their bar, as alſo my proteſt I delivered in againſt them, and my formall Appeal which I ſent unto the houſe of Commons from Newgate.</hi>
                  </note> And being there, <hi>I</hi> was by their Speaker, the Earle of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> preſſed at their bar (inquiſition like, againſt all law, and juſtice) to anſwer to Interrogatories againſt my ſelfe, without having any viſible accuſer or any accuſation at all laid unto my charge, which <hi>I</hi> pleaded at their bar, was againſt the very fundamentall lawes of the land, and ſo declared by themſelves, the 13. of <hi>February,</hi> 1645. in my own caſe, againſt the Star-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, but being eagerly preſſed to anſwer their interrogatories, I was driven to my laſt refuge, to proteſt againſt their aſſuming a juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on over me in a criminall caſe, being a Commoner, for which and nothing elſe, I was moſt illegally the 11. <hi>Iune,</hi> 1646. committed by them to <hi>Newgate,</hi> as your Excellency may read in the 7. pag. of my book, called <hi>the free mans freedome vindicated,</hi> now with the reſt of my bookes in the hands of Mr. <hi>Saxby,</hi> and the 16. of <hi>Iune</hi> 1646. I ſent my Appeale (appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from their juriſdiction) to the Houſe of Commons, which Appeal you may read ibim. pag. 9, 10. 11. which ſaid appeale the Houſe of Commons received read, and approved of, and committed it and my cauſe to a Committee where Col. <hi>Martin</hi> had the chaire, who twice examined the buſineſſe, but I could never get him to make his report unto the Houſe to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:161200:2"/> day, upon whoſe delay the Lords took courage and the 22 <hi>Iune</hi> 1646 ſent for me up to their barr, where they commnaded me to kneele, which I abſolutely refuſed, and ſtood ſtif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to my ſaid appeale, upon which they committed me cloſe priſoner to <hi>Newgate,</hi> and alſo ordered that <hi>I</hi> ſhould not be permited Pen, Ink, or Paper, or any to ſpeak with me, or to have acces to me in any kind, which order you may read in halfe a ſheete of paper called the Juſt man in Bonds, now alſo in Mr. <hi>Saxbyes</hi> hands; <hi>which ſaid order was ſo barbarouſly executed upon me, by Ralph Briſto the Clarke of Newgate, that my wife was not permitted to come into the priſonyard to ſpeak with me out of my window, neither was ſhee, my, ſervant, nor any of my friends p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>mitted to deliver into my hands, either meat, drink, money,</hi> or any other neceſſaries, till the 11 of <hi>July</hi> 1646. upon which day by a Warrant I was brought to the Lords Barr a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <note n="*" place="margin">iz. <hi>Mr. Sargant Finch, Mr. Hayle, Mr. Glover, and Mr. Hearne.</hi>
                  </note> of purpoſe to be ſuppriſed, they having had as I was inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, 3 or 4 Lawyers conſtantly at worke all the time <hi>I</hi> was cloſe, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly to draw up a charge againſt me, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>As you may more fully read in the</hi> 12, 13, 14, 15. <hi>pages of my Annotamy of the Lords tyrannay.</hi>
                  </note> and being at their barr <hi>I</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed againe to kneel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or to doe any action that might declare a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o their juriſdiction, <hi>telling the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> I <hi>was reſolved to ſpend the laſt drop of my heart blood in iuſtification of my Appeale to the Houſe of Commons</hi> * whereupon they then and there for ſo doing, ſentenced me in two ſeverall ſentences, to pay to the King 4000. <abbr>l.</abbr> to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonned in the (extraordinary chargeable priſon of the) Tower of <hi>London,</hi> for 7. yeares, without, according to the cuſtome of the place allowing me ſubſiſtance, and that I be for ever uncapable to beare any office or place, in military or in civill government, in Church or Common wealth, as more at large in the ſentence it ſelfe, printed in <hi>Vox Plebis,</hi> pag. 31, 32 33. 34. you may pleaſe to read. And being by warrant that day ſent to the Tower, where in my judgement I was very hardly uſed in many particulars, but eſpecially in being compulſively &amp; ſtrictly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorced from my wife, (that meet helpe that the wiſe and mercifull God had provided for me, to beare part of my afflictions) tell the 16. of <hi>September,</hi> 1646. about which time both ſhee and my ſelfe petitioned againe to the Houſe of Commons, which you may be pleaſed to read in the laſt end of my book called <hi>Londons liberty in Chains,</hi> with which Petitions ſhee with ſome ſcores of Gentlewomen her friends and mine, followed the Houſe day by day, with the importunate widowes crys for juſtice, to men abundantly more unjuſt then her unright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous judge, that upon no importunitie for theſe ſix yeares together, will doe me one dram of effective juſtice, though <hi>I</hi> dare boldly ſay <hi>I</hi> have ſpent one way and another, in following them, above a thouſand pound. But with her importunitie, the ſame Committee with ſome additions as <hi>I</hi> remember, was appointed by the houſe fully to here and report my buſineſſe, and after the greateſt part of twenty dayes waiting. <hi>I</hi> got the Committee fully to heare me, upom the 6. <hi>November</hi> 1647. at which <hi>time, Lievt. Gen. Cromwell, Col. Fleetword, and Maior Harriſon now with you were preſent,</hi> and ſo fully heard and know the whole ſtate of my buſineſſe that if their memory had not been very forgetfull, <hi>I</hi> ſhould have thought they ſhould have been able fully to have directed the <hi>Councell of Warre,</hi> to have deſired ſomething of the Houſe of Commons, that might really have been good for me, viz. <hi>without delay to have adiudged my cauſe and appeale, either to my iustification, or condemnation,</hi> which is the chiefeſt thing is the firſt place I deſire, and which may eaſily be done in one houre.</p>
               <p>Vpon the hearing fully of all buſineſſe, ſo that in 7. yeares time I know not what more effectually to ſay then then I did, <hi>I</hi> was commanded by that Committee, by the 9. of <hi>Novemb,</hi> 1646. to bring in writing what by word of mouth <hi>I</hi> had ſaid to them, which I accordingly
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:161200:2"/> did, and ſince printed it, and <hi>intituled it an Annotamy of the Lords tyrannie.</hi> And have ſince that time with all my might, by all the wayes and meanes I had in the world, indeavoured with Mr. <hi>Martin</hi> to make my report to the houſe, as you may fully underſtand, by reading the firſt part of my epiſtle to him, dated the 31. of <hi>May</hi> laſt, (which in print I lately ſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Excellency) and, in this incloſed epiſtle ſent unto him yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, <note n="*" place="margin">Which is now printed in the laſt pag. of my book, called Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nahs cryes out of the Whales bellie.</note> but what ſhould be the reaſon why he will not doe it, I cannot tell, unleſſe it be that he is conjoyned in intereſt with the Lords, to buy, ſell or betray the liberties of all the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> who are all and everie of them concerned in the Lords arbitrary and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall dealing with me, for what is my caſe to day, may be their caſe to morrow, and ſeeing by intreaties and faire words, I could doe nothing with him, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>But in anſwer to the forementioned let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he ſent me a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in which he gives me information, that he hath proferred</hi> 20. <hi>times to make my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, but the houſe would not heare him, and he alſo promiſeth me to doe it the firſt opportunitie he hath; which he did performe the</hi> 14. <hi>Sept.</hi> 1647. <hi>which hath given me ful ſatisfaction, which I have acknowledged to him in my late two printed letters to him.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>I</hi> underhand in City and Country applyed my ſelfe vigoruſly to my friends and fellow Commons, ſtrongly to peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Houſe of Commons, to adjudge my cauſe, and either to juſtifie me or condemne me, for favour or mercy I craved none from them but only law and juſtice, ſome of whoſe petitions, by the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of a company of tyrannicall, treacherous Villains there, <hi>Hollis and Stapleton, &amp;c.</hi> was ſlighted and would not be received, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers they burnt by the hands of the Common Hang-man, and for ever to terrifie the Commons of England againe to petition for ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice or their liberty, <hi>they moſt illegally and uniustly cauſed ſeverall of the Petitioners to be impriſonned,</hi> for which action alone, by the principles of juſtice and reaſon, they deſerve in my judgement to be hanged. And when I ſee that all my importunity and all the faire meanes <hi>I</hi> could uſe, would doe me no good; and knowing that<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it was as bad as murther in me, to leave any meanes whatſoever unattemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for my own preſervation, being by my tyrannicall impriſonment likely to be murthered and deſtroyed, without and againſt all law, and juſtice, and being in my own ſoule confidently perſwaded, that if <hi>I</hi> ſate ſtill <hi>I</hi> muſt periſh, I made a vigorus and ſtrong attempt upon the private Soldiery of your Army, and with abundance of ſtudy and paines, and the expence of ſome ſcores of pounds, I brought my juſt, honeſt, and lawfull in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, by my agents, inſtruments, and intereſt to a good ripeneſſe, not daring to meddle with the Officers, having had ſo large experience of the ſelfeiſhneſſe, and timerouſneſſ of the chiefeſt of them, ſitting in the Houſe of Commons, who I had ſufficiently tryed, to ſee what mettle they were made of, and found them quivering ſpirited, overwiſe, prudentiall men, not any one of them that I could heare of at any time daring to carrie a high, though juſt Petition into the Houſe, to deliver it, and ſpeake unto it, ſo that at preſent they were to me become reprobate ſilver, and therefore knowing by the morrall law, that murther was odious in the ſight of God, eſpecially ſelfe murther, I durſt not but doe the uttermoſt that I could to preſerve my ſelfe, which in my underſtanding could by no other meanes in the world be effected, but by men that had ſwords in their hands, and reſolution in their ſpirits, which I beleeve had been done ere now to the purpoſe, if I had imbraced their earneſt deſire to breake priſon and goe to them, which for divers weighty reaſons <hi>I</hi> could not, and truly Sir give me leave to tell you without feare or dread, had I come, and could have got ſo many to have followed me, as would da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e inabled me with my ſword in my hand, to have done ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and execution upon thoſe grand treacherous fellows, and tyrants at <hi>Weſtminſter,,</hi> that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:161200:3"/> have not only tyranniſed over me, but the whole kingdome, I ſhould have made no more ſcruple of conſcience with my own hands to have deſtroyed them, (who have deſtroyed all law and juſtice, equity and conſcience, and deſtroy us by their arbitrary and tyrannicall wills) then to have deſtroyed ſo many Weaſels and Poule-Cats; but <hi>I</hi> hoped the great worke of the kingdome would ſpeedily be done, by more abler and wiſer inſtruments then <hi>I</hi> judged my ſelfe to be, but when I ſee and heard of divers great ones in your Army to coole the buſineſſe on foot, <hi>I</hi> ſent my wife then big with child, and ſeverall other Agents down to St. <hi>Albons,</hi> to revive my earneſt deſire, with thoſe I had an intereſt in, for the obtaining of my juſt ends, <hi>iuſtice, and my iuſt liberty, never in my life time coveting or deſiring the intereſt and power of your Army to be a clooke or covering for any of my miſdoings;</hi> making alwayes ſo far as I knew, the law of the land the ſquare of my actions, in reference to civill things amongſt men, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving alwayes this rule of true reaſon and juſtice before me, <hi>to doe to every man, as I would have all men doe to me,</hi> but underſtanding from time to time of plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and contrived tricks put upon me &amp;c, by ſome faire outſides un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Who I have named in my booke called Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nahs cry, and in an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to Lievt. Gen. Cromwell, bearing date</hi> 13. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1647. <hi>and lately printed with my two letters to M. Hen. Martin.</hi>
                  </note> command, (although I never heard any thing of your gallant, juſt and magnanimous ſelfe, either in reference to me or the publique, but what deſerves my choiſeſt thankes and praiſes, and the rather for that I am as it were a meere ſtranger to you) which now to you, J iudge it altogether inconvenient to take the boldneſſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of, but hearing from time to time, <hi>I</hi> was not forgot amongſt thoſe, that have no more ends then I have, viz. <hi>iuſtice, and the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſall good and benefit of all iuſt intereſts in England.</hi> I waited with as much patience as my unſimpothized with condition would inable me to doe, for the good houre of my iuſt and long expected liberty, iuſtice and repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, procured for me, by the meanes of your ſelfe, and thoſe men of honour and juſtice with you.</p>
               <p>But moſt Noble, and moſt Honoured Gen. give me leave without your diſpleaſure, truly to tell you, that though <hi>I</hi> muſt (as you juſtly and truly deſerve from me) returne you extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary hearty thankes, for your chearefull willingneſſe to give countenance to anything that may juſtly be undertaken, (in my doulfull and ſad condition) <hi>to procure for me juſtice, and my juſt freedom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> yet I am apt to think there is intentively ſome tricks put upon me, by ſome of the contrivers <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>The cheif contrivers I</hi> iudge <hi>to be King, Crumwell, and his ſon Prince Ireton. who are the principall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments that keep me in priſon, becauſe I will not comply with their turncoat Lordly intereſt, and yet at that time durſt not well, but ſeem to doe ſomething far me in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the honeſt Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jutaters impertunitie, about it, but yet by their ſubtilty did it in ſuch a manner that they were ſure would doe me no good.</hi>
                  </note> of that paper to the Houſe of Commons, Dated at <hi>Reading Iuly</hi> 19. 1647. ſent by your Excellency and your Councell of Warr, for moſt Noble Sir, the thing that will doe me good is vigorrouſly to preſſe the Houſe of Commons, <hi>to command Mr. Martin to make my report unto</hi> their Houſe, <hi>and then to adjudge my cauſe,</hi> for either the Houſe of Lords have by law a Juriſdiction over me, and all the Commons of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land? in crimminall caſes, or they have not, and in my proteſting againſt the Lords juridiction, in crimminall caſes, and appealing to the Houſe of Commons, as my leagall &amp; proper judges <hi>I</hi> have ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther done evill, &amp; illegally, or elſe juſtly and legally, If <hi>I</hi> have done evilly and illegally I crave no favour at their hands, but deſire them to condemne me, that ſo <hi>I</hi> may know what to truſt to, that ſo I may vſe ſome meanes to the King &amp;c. for to the Houſe of (Lords I will never in this apply my ſelfe.) For the takeing of my 4000<abbr>l.</abbr> Fine, and reſtoring me to my liberty and freedome, and not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:161200:3"/> all my dayes to live in priſon, and in the concluſion be forced to ſtrave for want of bread, or elſe to eat my wife and children,</p>
               <p>But if in my proteſting againſt the Lords juriſdiction in crim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minall caſes, and appealing to the Houſe of Commons as my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and legall Iudges, I have done well and legally, <hi>why doe the houſe of Commons ſuffer me to be kept in priſon, and not adiudge my cauſe, and deliver me with iuſt reparation, and a iuſt puniſhment upon the cauſers of my cauſeleſſe torments and ſufferings,</hi> and this alone is the thing moſt noble Generall, I want and ſtand in need of, which only will doe me good, and which in it ſelfe is ſuch a rationall and equitable peece of juſtice, as by no iuſt man can be denyed.</p>
               <p>For alas, moſt noble Generall, what will liberty in England, without iudging my cauſe (and Appeale) doe me good, am I not ſubiect every houre in the Kings name and behalfe? though it may be againſt his previty, will or mind, to have my body caſt into priſon, for the 4000. l. which by that uniuſt fine I in law owe him? or if my body by abſence cannot be ſeized upon, is not that little that I have liable by the law every houre to be ſeized upon? yea, <hi>and the very beds that my diſtreſſed, helpeleſſe, and unpittied wife and children lye upon, ſubiect to be taken from under them, yea, and ſtript of their very wearing clothes</hi> They were, And truly Sir, ſo large experience have I of the mercileſſe and cruel temper of my adverſaries, that I will not truſt in the leaſt, to the mercie of the mercileſſe Lords at <hi>weſtminſter,</hi> or their cruell and mercileſſe confederates, in the Houſe of Commons, Aſſembly, or Common Counſell of London, any of whom I am ſure, would willingly, Vote, Petition, or Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate me to death.</p>
               <p>And againe Sir, ſhould I put in baile as your paper deſires, <hi>I</hi> ſhould run my ſelfe into ſuch a ſnare, as <hi>I</hi> ſhould never get out of again while I live, but thereby ſhould like a fooliſh fellow, undoe all that in the heat of the fire I have been doing almoſt this 14. moneths, viz. <hi>preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and defending the</hi> liberty of all the Commons of England, againſt the tyrannicall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſions of the Houſe of Lords<hi>:</hi> For whoſe priſoneram I? ſurely the Houſe of Lords, and no others, (unleſſe it be negligent <hi>Henry Martins)</hi> and to whom muſt <hi>I</hi> put in ſecurity? ſurely to no other then the Lords. And undoubtedly I ſhould both in reaſon and law, by ſo doing iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the illegallitie and uniuſtneſſe of their ſentence paſt againſt me, and not only ſo, but alſo iuſtifie their iuriſdiction and power over all the Commons of England in criminall caſes, which were an act, that would not only as much as in me lyes, deſtroy the beſt and funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentalleſt Lawes of England, (viz. <hi>Magna Charta, and the moſt excellent Petition of Right,</hi> &amp;c.) But alſo deſtroy and overthrow the <hi>rationall, naturall, nationall, and legall liberties of my ſelfe and all the Commons of England,</hi> which would be an act in my iudgement, not only of the greateſt buſineſſe in the world, but alſo of the greateſt treaſon that <hi>I</hi> could commit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the land of my nativitie and my own being, of which wickedneſſe I would not iuſtly be eſteemed guilty for all the gold in the world.</p>
               <p>Now moſt noble and heroicall Generall, if it ſhould be obiected againſt me, that the Houſe of Commons, are full of the great and weighty affaires of the Kingdome, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore want time to debate and adiudge my particular buſineſſe, to which I anſwer and ſay, <hi>I</hi> am confident they have not a buſineſſe of greater weight and conſequence before them, then mine in the latitude of it is, <hi>for it is concerning the eſcentiall and fundamentall liberties of themſelves, of me, and of all and every individuall Commoner of England,</hi> and I wonder what greater buſineſſe they can ſpend their time about, then a buſineſſe of ſo grand and univerſall concernment, without the ſettlement of which, it is eaſily to be evinced, that all that you have done with your ſwords, and they with their tongues is to no more purpoſe then to blow
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:161200:4"/> in the aire, <hi>for invaſion of rights, was the true cauſe of all the preſent warres,</hi> and their ſo vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible invading of the juſt and legall rights, and freedomes of all the Commons of England, is not the way in the leaſt to pacific and ſtill them, but to foment and newly increaſe them, and make them a freſh flame out againe <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſpccially when the Commons of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, ſhall ſee the moſt baſe and wicked jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of L. G. Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, and his' ſon Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton: whoſe power &amp; intereſt in the Army (by thoſe</hi> 4 <hi>grandiug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers means,</hi> viz. <hi>Lord Say, Lord Wbarton, young Sir Hen. Vaine, and Soliciter St. Iohn) is now vigoruſly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved to ſupport &amp; uphold the Lords u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpations, tyranny, and grand opproſſions, that ſo they may mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to be voted by them to be domincer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, tyranniſing Lords with them, or elſe why am I kept in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon by them, ſeeing it is every houre in the day in their power to deliver me if they plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi>
                  </note> with ſtrong violence which if it doe, I hope it will be to their fatall and finall deſtruction<hi>:</hi> which I with all my might and ſtrength with as much earneſtneſſe as <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> proſecuted the <hi>Philiſtems,</hi> ſhould helpe forward, though <hi>I</hi> ſhould thereby pull the roofe of the houſe about my eares as he aid.</p>
               <p>And truly Sir <hi>I</hi> cannot thinke that the Houſe of Commons are ſo mindfull of the good of the kingdome, that the providing therefore, ſo ſtraightens them, that they have no time to heare my report, and adiudge my cauſe. Sure I am ſince my report was ready, they have found time enough to vote and devide among themſelves like wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſtewards, hundreds of thouſands of pounds of their maſters the Common wealths money, and <hi>I</hi> am ſure they can find time enough to vote all the Commons of <hi>England</hi> ſlaves, by voting their honeſt and iuſt Petitions, to be burnt by the hands of the Common Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, yea and to vote and declare them Rebe'ls and Traytors to the kingdome, (which principally is themſelves) for endeavouring by petition to make known their grievances to them their ſervants, whom they chuſe and truſted to provide for their weal but not in the leaſt for their woe, 1. part book Decl. p. 150. And beſides they can find time to violate the lawes and iuſtice of the kingdome, by voting the 11. Members particularly impeached of no leſſe then high trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, by accuſers ready to proſecute and make good at their perrils their charge and impeachment, to have liberty without ſecuritie to travell where they pleaſe for ſix moneths, and yet can find no time in 13. moneths to deliver me from the tyranny of the Lords, who ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally laid no crime nor legall charge to my charge, nor never in the leaſt produced any accuſer or witneſſe againſt me, but meerly impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned me becauſe <hi>I</hi> would not be a ſlave to their tyrannicall wills and unbounded luſts, which is the hight of iniuſtice. <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>See Vox Plebis, pag.</hi> 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 18, 19. <hi>&amp;c. See my Annotamy of the Lords tyranny, p.</hi> 8.9.10. <hi>and my book cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the reſolved mans reſolution, dated</hi> 30. <hi>April</hi> 1647. <hi>p.</hi> 3, 4, 8, 9, 10. <hi>See alſo regall tyranny, from the</hi> 62. 63. <hi>to the</hi> 84. <hi>pag.</hi>
                  </note> Beſides Sir, if I had doe evill, add lying in priſon after ſo many Gaole detiveries, and being ſo ſtrongly committed by thoſe, that <hi>I</hi> am confident never a Iudge in <hi>Weſtminſter Hall,</hi> dare grant me a <hi>Habias Corpus</hi> againſt; there being no viſible and formall power in England but the Houſe of Commons, to ſave me from Arbitrary deſtruction, they ought by law, though never in my ſelfe ſo guilty of violation of the law, being the Lords have let ſo many Gaole deliveries paſſe, and hath never called me oat to erye me by law, nor yet to this day hath laid no legall crime to my charge, for by the law of England (which they havee often ſworne to maintaine) there ought to be Gaole deliveries held 3. times a yeare, or oftner if need require, either for the condemning or acquitting all priſoners whatſoever, 5 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3 2. 4. part <hi>Sir Edward Cookes inſtitutes,</hi> folio. 168, 169. <hi>See the oppreſſed mans oppreſſions declared.</hi> pag. 3. And <hi>Ionah cryes outt of the Whales belly</hi> pag. 10. See alſo the beginning of <hi>Vox Plebis.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:161200:4"/>
               <p> And Sir, give me leave to tell you, <hi>I</hi> am as free a man, and have as good a right to the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of all the lawes in England as any Member of the Houſe of Commons what ever he be, (as they confeſſe in their own Declarations, cited by me, in the <hi>Outcryes of Oppreſſed Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, for all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ir vapring with their b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g ſwolne blatherly priviledges,</hi> they having none at all in referrence to the Commons of England. <hi>But freedome from arreſts, and that but for a ſhort time, and that not for aprenti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſhip,</hi> much leſſe for ever, being as lyable to the law as any other man, either for the breach of the peace, Fellony or Treaſon, as <hi>Sir Edward Cooke</hi> their own learned oracle declares in the 4 <hi>part of his inſtitutes, chap. high Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, fol.</hi> 25. And I find by his diſcourſe there, that they have no priviledges by law in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrence to the King, <hi>but freedome of ſpeech and debate, and that he ſhall not take notice of any thing done and debated among themſelves, tell they themſelves in a Parliamentary way tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the cogniſance of it to him.</hi> And if this be true as that learned Lawyer, &amp;c. declares it is, then I humbly deſire the preſſing of this argument unto the houſe without any more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, at leaſt at preſent to deliver me, <hi>becauſe</hi> I <hi>have laine ſo long in priſon without any legall accuſation at all, or legall tryall, or ſo much as without any proſecuter or informer againſt me at all,</hi> which is againſt all law and iuſtice in the higheſt degree whatſoever, for the words of their own late Vote in the behalfe of the eleaven impeached Members is.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That by the law of the Land, no Iudgement can be given to ſuſpend (and therefore much leſſe</hi> to impriſon) <hi>thoſe members from ſitting in the Houſe, upon the papers preſented by the Army,</hi> before <hi>particulars produced and proofs made,</hi> &amp; if this be true, then I am ſure they are moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt in not delivering me, who orriginally never had any charge at all againſt me, <hi>nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſee proſecuter nor witneſſe examined againſt me, to this very day;</hi> O hight of injuſtice, and partiallity? thus to vote, and thus contrary to that vote, to deale with me, who am equally free and intaled to the Law of the Land as any of their Members.</p>
               <p>But yet moſt Noble ſir, give me leave to aver unto you that I am not only illegally impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned, but that their vote in favour of their impeached members is moſt illegall in it ſelfe, and againſt the law, and the practiſes of the law in England, or elſe they themſelves violated it in the higheſtd degree with the Earle of Straford, who upon a generall charge of high trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, without mentioning particulars, <hi>further then for endeavouring to ſubvert the Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Lawes, without nameing any witneſſes or</hi> proſecutors, unleſſe it was their own Clarke, and yet required at the nick of time, not only to ſequeſter him, from the Houſe of Lords, but alſo to ſecure his body in priſon, which was accordingly done at the very inſtant, and then, and not before examined witneſſes againſt him, and out of their examinations, drew par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular articles, to make good their generall Charge, and <hi>I</hi> have from good hands been told, <hi>Mr Hallis under hand, was one of his chiefe proſecutors, and ſat up many a late night to beat his braines to deſtroy him,</hi> and therefore juſt, or not juſt, it is but juſt, that he himſelfe ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aft of his own law, which he &amp;c. is ſo farr from doing, that he is yet at liberty, and voted by the Houſe to have leave for 6 monthes to goe whether he pleaſeth, the which if the Army with patience ſuffer, I am ſure their credet is loſt forever, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>And now it is too apparent that Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well and Ireton, there theſe impeachers, with their fore mentioned aſſociates here at</hi> Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter, <hi>deſired no more but to be rid of their company, that ſo they might not ſtand in their way, as an anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to hinder them from their tyranicall intended tyrany and Lordly domination, now as apparant to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny impartiall obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant rationall man as the Sun that ſhines at noone day.</hi>
                  </note> and all men will conclude they can prove nothing againſt them. Sir I have ſtated my caſe to you, and muſt crave pardon for my teadiouſneſſe, leaving all to your judicious and wiſe conſideration, to doe in it as God, juſtice, humanity, and conſcience ſhall direct you; craving nothing from your power to juſtifie or protect me in any evill, or wickedneſſe; but only that <hi>I</hi> may have juſtice and faire play above board, and upon them tearmes I bid defiance to all the adverſaries I have in England; to doe the worſt they can to me, only I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:161200:5"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:161200:5"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:161200:6"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:161200:6"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:161200:7"/> and earneſtly ſupplycate you, that what you ſhall reſolve to doe for me, you doe it ſpeedily and vigorouſly, for perriſh <hi>I</hi> can not, nor will not if <hi>I</hi> can help it, and if nothing will ſerve the 2 Houſes but my cauſleſſe deſtruction, I am neſſceſitated like a plaine dealer, that feares no cullers, <hi>to proteſt unto your</hi> Excellency <hi>that if ſpeedily they will not doe me juſtice I will appeale to all the Commons of England,</hi> and the private Soldiers of your Army, <note n="*" place="margin">Which I had done eare now if I had not been deluded With faire words, and cheate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with faire promiſes,</note> and doe the beſt <hi>I</hi> can to ſet them about their eares, to cut their tyrannicall throats, though I periſh with them; ſo committing your Renowned Excellency, to the faithfull protection, care and direction of your wiſe and powerfull God, deſireing of him for you, that your heart may be kept upright, and ſinſcere before him, tell the Glorious and joyfull appearing of our Capt. Gen. the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and ſo I humbly take my leave and ſubſcribe my ſelfe</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>From my watch Tower, in the Tower of</hi> London, <date>
                        <hi>this</hi> 22. Iuly, 1647.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute> 
                  <signed> Your Excellencies cordiall, obleiged and faithfull ſervant for the common good of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, ready to ſpend his heart blood with you. Iohn Lilburne.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The ſecond Letter thus followeth. For his Excellency, Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> this at <hi>Kingſtone</hi> preſent with ſpeed.</head>
               <p>NOble and right worthy Gen. vouchſafe unto me <hi>I</hi> beſeech you leave, to preſent unto your Excellency, the gratefull acknowledgement of my heart for your Excellencies ſenceableneſſe of my affl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctions, and your readines and willingneſſe to improve your intereſt to abaite them, and particularly for your late Noble favour which <hi>I</hi> was made partaker of, by the hands of your Secretary; and give me leave humbly to acquaint your Excellency, that by my wiſe who hath bin all the by paſt weeks at <hi>Kingson,</hi> to ſee what ſhe could do for my liberty, <hi>I</hi> received a meſſage by her coming from ſome of no ſmall influence and <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Viz Mr. Allen one of the Adjetators for L. G. Cromwels Regia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and his Offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry creature in the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying of al his ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and parts to make fruitleſſe the honeſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiations of the honeſt and uncorrupted adje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tators, and to ſupport the uſurping Lords in their tyrannicall op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, as I have largely declared unto himſelfe in my letter unto him of</hi> 23 <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt</hi> 1647,</note> parts <hi>that I ſhould petition to the Lords for my liberty as the only way to procure it,</hi> which advice is as acceptable to me as to deſire me with my own hands to cut my own throt, and little ſhould <hi>I</hi> have exſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have received any ſuch prenitious diſtructive advice (to juſtice and true freedome) from the mouthes of any in your Army, that hath eminently pretended to be patrons of true, and impartially juſtice, and the Commons true legall and well knowne privelidges; &amp; therfore fearing that by the deſtructive advice, or incinuating inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of ſome about you that pretendedly would ſerve me, you ſhould be put upon ſome addreſſes to the Lords for me, the thoughts of which <hi>I</hi> can not but in iuſtice and honeſty abhor and deteſt, and had rather deſire to rot here then not with all my intereſt as farre as <hi>I</hi> am able to hinder ſuch a thing, for to the barr of the great intereſt of the Commons of England I have appealed in the iuſtifiing and pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſenting of which appeal I will live and die; ſtand or fall <hi>I</hi> deſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothing but either legall iuſtification or condemnation and theree<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ore moſt Noble Gen. if there be no other meanes within your
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:161200:7"/> power to eaſe me of my ſorrowes and to obtaine iuſtice, for me and all the Commons of England concerned in me, but by applycation to the Lords, I moſt humbly and moſt earneſtly beſeech and intreat your Honour to diſiſt and throw my buſineſſe behind your back, and forever to bury it in the grave of forgitfulneſſe, and truly <hi>I</hi> cannot but apprehend that this advice flows from the ſame intreſt, <hi>that over ruled the rational &amp; juſt diſenters at that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Warr,</hi> that ſent up their deſires to the Parliament the other day, that I might put in bail for my liberty, the ſnares of which deſires <hi>I</hi> took the boldneſſe largely to evince in my letter of the 22 <hi>July</hi> 1647. to your Honour.</p>
               <p>And Noble ſir, though it ſhould or might be ſaid to me that the Lords are growne, very gallant, and for now in honeſty outſtrip the preſent Houſe of Commons, &amp; therfore ſit for me to comply with and addreſſe unto; yet give me leave to tell your Excellency, <hi>I walk not, nor act not from accidents, but from principals, and being throughly perſwaded in my own ſoule they are iuſt, righteous, and honeſt,</hi> I <hi>will by Gods goodneſſe never depart from them though I periſh in maintaining them;</hi> and not only the principals of reaſon, but the known and iuſt law of England, and the experience of all ages tels me, that the uſurpations of ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall prerogative Lords, over honeſt and free Commons: is not only diſtructive to true juſtice and right reaſon <hi>(the fountaine of all iuſt lawes)</hi> but alſo to all true and iuſt freedome, and therefore I both muſt and will run the hazard of ſpending my heart blood, to root up and deſtroy their illegall and uniuſt uſurpations, being now ſo deeply ingaged, and can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver willingly without being a Trayter to my ſelf and Country, conſent in this to cloſe, with them, knowing very well, that it is an eaſie thing for a ſcholmaſters to make a t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>merous boy for the ſaving of himſelfe, to ſay and doe what he pleaſeth, when he hath taken him in a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious crime, and hath got his breeches downe, with a good rod in his hand, to whip him ſoundly, and yet as ſoone as tha: preſent feare is over, to be as ready as ever, to run into the ſame tranſgreſſion, and truly moſt Noble Sir, give me leave to think, that if the preſent Houſe of Lords were truly and in good ſerious earneſt, reſolved to repent of their evils, and amend their wayes by doing unbiaſed juſtice and right, they would of themſelves without any addreſſing unto, have forthwith done juſtice and right to me, and other afflicted one whom they have by unmerciful impriſonments contrary to all equity, reaſon, law, and juſtice, yea and <hi>I</hi> dare boldly ſay it, againſt the light of their own conſciences; And truly Sir, give me leave to aſſure your Honour from the mouthes of ſome of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to ſome of my true friends. I might at the firſt Conteſt with them have had my liberty, &amp;c. from them, if I would in any way of my own framing, have made but any addreſſes to them. And truly Sir give me leave in the ſincerity and uprightneſſe of my heart before the preſence of God to tell you, it is meerly a principle of conſcience within me, to juſtice and honeſty, and not any wilfull ſtubbornneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or baſe ſelfe ends of my owne, that makes me I cannot, ingeneouſly profeſſing unto your honour, I received more, iuſtice and courteſie in three moneths from the Houſe of Lords, then <hi>I</hi> have done almoſt in ſeaven yeares from the Houſe of Commons. And I doe proteſt before the Almighty, (and <hi>I</hi> appeale unto the Lord <hi>Wharton</hi> to beare <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto whom I ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my proteſt before</hi> I <hi>delivered it, and told him both what I muſt and would and offered him to doe any thing that the Lords in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or iuſtice could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of me, ſo they would not force me to to their bar. See the</hi> 4. <hi>pag. of my booke, called the free mans freedome vindicated.</hi>
                  </note> me witneſſe) that <hi>I</hi> did the utmoſt that in me laid by way of gratitude and thankefulneſſe unto them to hinder a conteſt with them, but the revenging mallice of the Earle of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> (who I am apt to think had long ſince loſt his head, for his baſe and palpable treacherie, and tranſcendent wickedneſſe, if Lievtenant Generall <hi>Cromwell</hi> had ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually diſcharged his duty to the whole kingdome as he ought to have done) at me, for ingaging with Lievtenant Generall <hi>Cromwell,</hi> in his juſt cauſe againſt him, would be ſatisfied with no reaſon, but the cruſhing me to peices, by whoſe meanes principally, with <hi>Col.</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:161200:8"/> 
                  <hi>Edward King,</hi> one of his treacherous wicked confederates, I ſuffer all that <hi>I</hi> doe at this day, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>See my printed nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative to the Ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the</hi> 21. <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1647. <hi>printed at the laſt on of the</hi> 2. <hi>Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my Epiſtle to Iudge Reeves.</hi>
                  </note> and <hi>I</hi> dare confidently affirme it, that if I could have addreſſed to them ſince my Appeale to the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, I might have had ſolid grounds, not only to have had my li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty: and my fine of 4000. <abbr>l.</abbr> taken of, but alſo ſome thouſands of pounds by their meanes in my purſe, which now in my thoughts is a very great hazzard whether ever <hi>I</hi> ſhall injoy or no.</p>
               <p>Therefore to conclude all. <hi>I</hi> ſhall humbly ſtate a caſe unto your Excellency, and leave the application of it to your ſelfe, which is this. An honeſt and a true man is following his lawfull occaſions, and there meets with him a company of bloody Murtherers, Theeves and Robber, who being ſtronger then he, ſet upon him, and attempt the taking away his purſe and life, and whiie he is ſtrugling with them, by comes a company of honeſt and true men, ſtronger then the Rogues and Theeves, unto whom the honeſt, almoſt deſtroyed man addreſſeth himſelf, and acquaints them truly &amp; fully with his preſent caſe, and pittifully cryes out to them for helpe, but they though they ſeeme to pittie him in words, paſſe by him and doe not effectually reſcue him, by meanes of which he is not only rob'd, but alſo ſlaine and deſtroyed. Now the queſtion is, whether by the law of humanity, nature and reaſon, the aforeſaid honeſt paſſengers were not tyed in duty and conſcience without any more diſpute, to have at leaſt reſcued the honeſt oppreſſed man, and have ſet him free? (or at leaſt to have ſecured him and them to the next juſt Magiſtrate) and endeavoured the obtaining of iuſtice for him, upon thoſe that would have deſtroyed him. And then the ſecond queſtion is, whether or no that in the caſe before mentioned, they ſuffer him (being eaſily able to reſcue him) to be robd and murthered? whether in the ſight of God and all iuſt men, they be not cleerly acceſſaries of the robberie and murther? and as guilty of it as thoſe that committed it. So craving pardon for my boldneſſe and tediouſneſſe, I commit you as my owne ſoule to the carefull and powerfull protection of the Lord <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah,</hi> deſiring of him for you, to mainetaine and uphold you, in your integrity and true plain uprightneſſe, that you may ſhine and be truly glorious in the eyes of our Lord and maſter, and all iuſt men, I humbly take my leave and reſt.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>From my cauſeleſſe and uniuſt inthralment, in the Tower of</hi> London, <date>
                        <hi>this</hi> 21. <hi>of Auguſt,</hi> 1647.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute> 
                  <signed>
                     <hi> your moſt devoted faithfull ſervant, that without feare or flattery highly honours you.</hi> John Lilburne.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Advice to the Private Soldiers.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIRS,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>MY beſt advice at your earneſt deſire, unto you and all the privat Soldiers of your Army is<hi>:</hi> to the death to conteſt for the preſervation and performing of your <hi>Solemn in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement,</hi> made and ſubſcribed at <hi>New Market</hi> the 5. th. <hi>July</hi> 1647. eſpecially in the firſt branch thereof: and not to ſuffer any thing to be acted or done in the Army, to the violati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, but forthwith vigorouſly to demand juſtice upon every perſon, though never ſo great, that you can prove hath or doth attempt the infringment of it, and to ſet a brand of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy upon him as a deceiver, and a man not fit to be intruſted, and alſo immediately to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire an account of your reſpective Adjutators, what they have been doing all this while: and ſuffer not one ſort of men too long to remaine adjetators, leaſt they be corrupted by bribes of offices, or places of preferment, <hi>for ſtanding waters though never ſo pure at firſt, in time putrifies,</hi> and alſo inſtantly preſſe your Adjutators to move vigorouſly for the imedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate and totall purgeing of the Houſe of all thoſe that ſat in Mr. <hi>Pellums</hi> factious traiterous <hi>Juncto:</hi> who are ſo declared already by your Army? by whoſe illeagall pretended and unbin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding votes, a new Warr was <hi>defacto</hi> raiſed and leavied in the Kingdome, to the viſible ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:161200:8"/> of the ruine and utter deſtruction there<hi>:</hi> and if you doe not this effectually, but for the factious Lordly ends of ſome great ones (as L. <hi>G. Crumwell, Commiſary Gen, Ireton)</hi> ſuffer that factious illeagall Combination and aſſembly of men, to run away with the name and power of a true Houſe of Commons, then it will evidently follow, that your Generall and your whole Army, and all thoſe members of the Houſe that came to you, and adheared to you, are all Parliament Rebels and traytors, inforceably oppoſing them, and marching up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them in all Warrlick manner, as you have done, and by your Remonſtrances, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, and propoſals, declaring that whole aſſembly of Mr. <hi>Pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes Juncto</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>See the latter end of the Armies Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance of</hi> 18. Auguſt, 1647. <hi>publiſhed to the wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>le Kingdome, by the ſpeſciall order of the preſent Houſe of Peeres,</hi> 20. Aug. 1647. <hi>ſee alſo the Adiutators propoſals or addreſſes 5th, and</hi> 14. Auguſt, 1647. <hi>subſcribed by</hi> 53 <hi>of their hands, and printed by the Armies printer.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>blades</hi> to be uſurpesr of a Parliament power, Traytor and enmies to their Country, and the truſt repoſed in them, ands fit to beſeverely puniſhed, and not fit to be continued any longer as Iudges in the Kingdome, or their own cauſes; and their ſitting ſtill in the Houſe will reader all the orders and ordinances made while they there ſit to be queſtionable, as unvailed and unbinding, being made by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>currant votes of ſo many as you your ſelves, &amp; al thoſe members that concurd with you, (but eſpeſcially the preſent Houſe of Lords) have ſo viſibly and publiquely declared Traytors to the whole Kingdome, and therefore are not fit to be law makers, nor Iudges in their own cauſes, and the greateſt and weightieſt things of the Kingdome, and beſides how can you, or any that have adhear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to you (in iuſtice) preſſe for the puniſhing of any in <hi>London,</hi> that was active in leaving War againſt you the Kingdoms &amp; Parliaments Army, as you call your ſelves, in your notable and large Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance of the 18 <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1647. ſeeing what they did, was in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Parliament authority, if you ſuffer the moſt, or any of Mr. <hi>Pellums Iuncto Blades,</hi> to ſet in the Houſe, and ſo to goe ſcot free without punniſhment, for to let the principals, (the Parliament men) goe free without punniſhment, and to punniſh the acceſſaries, the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens) for putting in execution their orders and ordinances; is the greateſt <hi>in iuſtice that can be acted in the World,</hi> and beſides, if that any of the <hi>Juncto Blades</hi> that ſat in the Houſe, when the votes paſſed, <hi>for leavying a new warr on the Kingdome, ſit ſtill in the Houſe and ſo gac on unpunniſhed:</hi> &amp; the active zealous <hi>Presbyter</hi> Citizens that did obey, &amp; execute their Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſhall any way be punniſhed, therefore what will this elſe, but be a iuſt ground to all rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall men to combine together, and reſolve in future time, never to obey any more orders, Ordinances of Parliament: leaſt they be by the Parliament ſoundly puniſhed therefore: <note n="*" place="margin">And for Sir Thomas Fairſax to command a Soldier to goe charge ſuch an enemie, and do the beſt he can to kill him, and when the obedient Soldier hath zealouſly put his command in execution, and for Sir Thomas when he hath done to goe about to hang the Soldier for his paines, is not only the hight of in iuſtice, but is alſo the ready way to breed a muteny in his Army that in future times, his commands will never be obeyed.</note> and grant that <hi>Iuncto</hi> to be a Houſe of Commons in any ſence, and all the late active zealous Citizens againſt you are acquited thereby from all their Junquits and made iuſt perſons, and your ſelves the Traytors and tranſgreſſors, and it may be, before you be a yeare older, yee may get your recompence by looſing your lives at Tiburne, or elſe wheare, as you will iuſtly diſerve it. In this particular you play the Iuglers, or ſuffer your ſelves to be foold, and doe not effectually ſee fulfilled, your own forementioned Declarations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore ſay I, immediately preſſe vigoruſly for the totall purging the Houſe of all that ſate with Mr. Pillam, that ſo there may be way made for the exemplary puniſhing of the Lord Maior of London, and all the chief ring-leaders, actors in the late deſperate and trayterous ingagement.</hi> And alſo preſſe for moneys to pay your quarters, the want of which will ſpeedily (by free quarter) deſtroy the Army in the poore country peoples affections, whoſe burthens are into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable, in paying Exciſe for that very meat the Soldiers eate from them gratis, and yet paying heavie taxations beſides, and being alſo lyable by the <hi>Perſons and Impropriators,</hi> to be every
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:161200:9"/> yeare robbed of the tenth part of their labours, ſtock, <hi>
                     <hi rend="sup">i</hi>
                  </hi> and increaſe, <hi>under the name of payment of Iewiſh Tythes, long ſince by the death of Chriſt abolſhed, Heb.</hi> 7. 5. 11. 12. 18. 19. 17. &amp; 9. 9. 12. 14. 16. &amp; 10. 1. 12.</p>
               <p>And if they be any thing ſtuborne in this particular of parting with their proper goods, to thoſe that never ſweat for it, <hi>then by the late Independant Ordinance of Parliament, they are ſubiect</hi> by the Arbitrary pleaſure of two Iuſtices of peace to pay them trible. Alſo it is worth your conſideration to preſſe that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> publique treaſure of the kingdome may be taken out of that uncertaine, cheating and coſoning way of receiving and paying, that now it is in, and put immediately into the old, experienced, ſure, and undeceiving way of the Exchequer, by meanes of which the Kingdome may be ſure to know what is done with their money.</p>
               <p>And without which both they and you wil be everlaſtingly conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and cheated <note n="*" place="margin">Read a late notable book intituled an eye ſalve for the Army.</note> but above all <hi>preſſe for the immediate doing of impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial iuſtice without any more delay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>ail men without exceptions,</hi> that are under oppreſſions &amp; ſuffer wrong, &amp; down withal ſorts and kinds of Monopolies, that ſo all the people may inioy their birth right, free trade. And take effectuall care of all our lawes and the proceedings therein, may be tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſpeedily into Engliſh that ſo the people may ſpeedily inioy ſome fruits by all your b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng and gallant promiſes, and may no longer have overmuch cauſe to ſay as now commonly they doe both in City and Country, <hi>that you have cheated and guld them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with faire and plauſible Declarations, which when you made, you never intended (as by your preſent actions you fully declare) to endeavour the fulfilling of, but made them as ſtalking Horſes to attaine your own ends, (of preſent power, and future expected honour and profit,</hi> and ſo ſuck the people dry, and make them ſlaves,) as the Grandees in Parliament have done with all their Declarations.</p>
               <p>But above all the reſt be ſure not to truſt your great officers at the Generalls quarters, no further then you can throw an Oxe, for they are generally corrupted, <hi>and to the true and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall liberties of the Commons of England are turned enemies and reprobates, being grown Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſelfe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh in the higheſt nature</hi> (having by their plauſible but yet cunning and ſubtile pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies, moſt uniuſtly ſtolne the power both from your honeſt Generall, and your too flexible Adiutators, and devolved it upon a company of corrupt Linſey woolſey men ſitting at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter.</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Who I am ſure are not ſhort in acting all manner of tyranny and appreſſion whaſoever, that may render a power or Magiſtracy, to be for fitters of their truſt, and degenerate from the true Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates into reall Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants.</note> 
                  <hi>That in Iune or Iuly laſt declared you Traytors for endeavo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ng by petition to make knowne your grievances to them, and in Auguſt laſt, voted and leavied a warre againſt you, intentively to have mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered and deſtroyed you.</hi> Whoſe principall care in all their viſible actions, is to rob and pole the poore kingdome of all their treaſure, and ſhare it by thouſands and ten thouſands, amongſt themſelves, and <hi>to doe effectuall iuſtice and right to no man, but themſelves, kindred and friends.</hi> Who by the ſerious of all their viſible actions, intend when the people are poore enough to make both them and you their vaſſells and ſlaves, and themſelves domineering Lords and maſters over you, and your aforeſaid officers preſent carriage being ſuch, as that they give too iuſt cauſe to me, &amp;c, to aver it under my hand, <hi>with ſorrow and griefe,</hi> that as ſure as <hi>I</hi> beleeve there is a God, ſo ſurely doe <hi>I</hi> beleeve that they are ioyned with the Lords againſt me, and become the principall inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to keep me faſt in my uniuſt impriſonment, witnes my hand this 8. Sept. 1647.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Iohn Lilburne.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
